A Guide to the School of Music Scrapbooks, 1915-1999 (bulk 1969-1999): UA 0048
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
School of Music Scrapbooks,
1915-1999 (bulk 1969-1999)
Special Collections, James Madison University
James Madison University School of Music
UA 0048
3.85 cubic feet; 5 boxes
The School of Music Scrapbooks, 1915-1999 (bulk 1969-1999), consist of 18 scrapbooks and loose ephemera. These scrapbooks predominantly chronicle the events of the Madison College Chorale between 1969 and 1997 under the direction of David A. Watkins, with other scrapbooks including one for the Women's Concert Choir under the direction of Sally M. Lance and another for the Madison College Glee Club under the direction of Edna T. Shaeffer.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the James Madison University School of Music on September 27, 2018.
Appraisal Note
Included in the transfer was a plaque, dated March 31, 1991, given to the "Madison Singers" (addressed to David Watkins) for performing at an Easter Service at Natural Bridge Village. The accompanying letters were retained, but the plaque was returned to the donor. A CD of a 1976 Spring performance containing sacred and secular music sung by the Madison College Chorale was also included in the transfer. It was also returned to the donor due to duplication in the Music Library holdings.
Administrative History
The James Madison University School of Music began as a single department when the school was founded in 1908. In 1909, the Glee Club was formed by department head Lida P. Cleveland, and became one of the prominent vocal groups of the university. After Cleveland's retirement in 1915, Edna T. Shaeffer led the vocal group until 1956, and helped it become recognized at the local and state level as one of the premier college vocal groups during the mid-twentieth century. As the university began to change and the School of Music expanded its list of programs, the Glee Club became known as the Madison College Concert Choir. The creation of the Madison College Chorale during the 1970s began to flourish under the direction of David A. Watkins (known affectionately as "Daddy Dave" by his students) from 1967 to 1999. That group (along with the Madison Singers, taught by Watkins until his retirement) remains one of the more prestigious and selective vocal choirs on campus. Sally M. Lance also worked with the department of music as a vocal instructor from 1969 to 1997 and led groups such as the Women's Concert Choir.
Scope and Content
The School of Music Scrapbooks, 1915-199 (bulk 1969-1997), consists of 18 scrapbooks and loose ephemera. These scrapbooks predominantly chronicle the events and interactions of the Madison College Chorale between 1969 and 1997, and also include one scrapbook for the Women's Concert Choir (1984-1985) under the direction of Sally M. Lance and one for the Madison College Glee Club under the direction of Edna Shaeffer. The photos of the Madison College Chorale are usually candid shots of students and their director, David Watkins, during numerous events of the school year. Loose ephemera include a mix of unlabeled and labeled photographs of performances and thank-you letters from numerous patrons and hosts from past events.
The content within the Madison College Chorale Scrapbooks usually all follow a similar timeline: a fall picnic where everyone gets to know each other and reconnect, preparing for the annual Christmas Vespers Concert, a singing tour to numerous locations around Virginia (including Williamsburg, the Tidewater region, and Northern Virginia), and ending with a spring picnic, pictures of executive board members, or miscellaneous candid photos. Some notable years include the scrapbooks for the Madison College/JMU Chorale 1970-1985 in which there are numerous captions for each photo detailing the comradery of the performers, and the JMU Chorale scrapbook for 1995-1996 for its colorful and unique design. The Glee Club Scrapbook focuses heavily on the history of the club until 1956, while the Women's Concert Choir focuses mainly on program photographs and choir news.
Arrangement
The scrapbooks are arranged chronologically. The loose ephemera is housed at the end of the collection.
Related Material
Edna T. Shaeffer Retirement Letters, 1940, 1956, SC 0061 Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Separated Material
A vinyl titled Madison College Chorale (1971-1972 Concert Season) has been removed from the collection and cataloged separately.
Bibliography
Baughman, Amanda J. James Madison University: A Century of Music. Harrisonburg: James Madison University, 2008.
Estock, Dr. Joseph J. Departmental Self-Studies for the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools: From the School of Fine Arts. Harrisonburg: James Madison University, 1981.
Lane, F. Douglas. Music at Madison: 1908-1988. Harrisonburg: James Madison University, 1989.
Music Self-Study Report, Feb. 1998, pt. 1, box 6, folder 1, Academic Affairs: Academic Program Reviews, 1976 - present (bulk 1992 - present), UA 0002, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College -- History; Madison College -- Students; James Madison University -- History; James Madison University -- Students; Choirs (Music); Glee clubs; Student activities; College students
Genre and Form Terms:
Scrapbooks; Photographs; Printed Ephemera
- Glee Club Scrapbook, 1915-1956 (Box OV 1)
- Madison College Chorale Scrapbook, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
- Madison College Chorus Scrapbook, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
- James Madison University Women's Concert Choir Scrapbook, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- James Madison University Chorale and Madison Singers Scrapbook, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1997 (Box 3)
- James Madison University Chorale Scrapbook, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
- Loose Photographs, 1946, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Loose Glee Club Scrapbook Ephemera, 1947-1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Loose Choral Programs, 1969-1970, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Loose Madison College Chorale Photographs, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Loose Thank You Letters, 1991, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)